so now that we know what locality is
let's see how do we use it to improve
data accesses first we will look at an
example that considers borrowing books
from the library in this example the
library represents a data repository
that is large so a lot of data there but
it is very slow to access we need to go
there find the book in the building
check it out bring it back home and so
on when we are borrowing books from the
library typically there is a lot of
temporal locality to it for example if
we are a student we might need to look
up the definition of locality very often
while we're studying and usually also
there is a lot of spatial locality to
using books for example if we look at
some computer architecture definition
ones we are likely to be looking up
other computer architecture stuff too in
the near future so continuing our
library based locality in data access
example we have seen that the library is
large but very slow to access and it
accesses to information in the library
have temporal and spatial locality
usually so when a student needs a piece
of information from the library what
should he do should he go to the library
find information read it and then just
go back home
should he borrow the book take it home
so that future accesses to the
information in the book are much faster
or should he take all the books and then
build a library at home let's consider
each of these three options if we go to
the library every time we need something
we're wasting a lot of time finding the
books and then looking up only one piece
of information and then returning the
book because we know that there is both
temporal and spatial locality which
means we will be probably reading the
same book and nearby books very often so
the problem with this approach is that
it does not benefit from locality and
this is why typically people do not use
it when they need to study a topic and
use library resources if we go to the
library and borrow the book we break it
home and now we have the book on the
topic that we are currently working on
close to us so this is an approach that
does exploit temporal and spatial
locality and eliminates the problem of
the
library being large and slow because we
have very few books bottled at home so
we can quickly find what we need in them
this is why most people will use this
option the approach of taking all the
books in building a library at home is
very expensive and also provides very
little benefit yes it saves us the trip
to the library and back but it doesn't
save us the time of searching among many
books finding them on the shelves and so
on so really we'd rather have relatively
few books that we are currently
interested in then have many books and
have to look them up very slowly so just
like people when faced with these
choices about the library usually choose
the second option because it's a good
trade-off between being able to find the
information quickly and not being
overwhelmed with the quantity of
information that we have brought in when
we have a processor that needs to access
main memory we will use the same
approach instead of going to memory for
every single memory location we will
bring the content of memory locations
that we are interested in closer to us
but we will try not to bring too much
close to us because that will result in
a very slow structure close to us so we
will again have slow accesses so what we
want is something small that keeps only
the information we are really interested
in and that small repository of
information is called a cache when we
are talking about memory accesses